Guide to the Mathew B. Brady and Levin Corbin Handy Photographic Studios Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mathew B. Brady and Levin Corbin Handy Photographic Studios Collection
1843-1957
1860-1935
GEN MSS 580
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
28.44
(76 boxes)
Photographs, papers, and artifacts created or collected by Mathew B. Brady, Levin Corbin handy, their studios, and their family, 1843-1957. The collection includes images created by Brady during the American Civil War and documents the continual use of these images into the early twentieth century by Handy and his studio. The collection reflects the operations of the Brady and Handy studios in Washington, D.C., from the middle of the nineteenth century through the early twentieth century. It contains work by other photographers and other studios collected by Handy, as well as camera lenses and other photographic artifacts. A small group of papers document aspects of the extended Handy family history.
Brady, Mathew B., approximately 1823-1896
Handy, Levin C. (Levin Corbin), 1855-1932
Jarvis, J. F. (John Fillis), 1849-1931
Russell, Andrew J., 1829-1902
L. C. Handy Studio
Underwood & Underwood
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the William Reese Company on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Mathew B. Brady (circa 1823-1896)
Mathew B. Brady (circa 1823-1896) was an American photographer who achieved prominence through his portrait photographs and his organization of photographers to document the American Civil War from his studio in Washington, D.C.
Born in Warren County, New York, to Irish immigrant parents, Brady learned the daguerreotype process in Saratoga, New York. By 1844, he operated a daguerreotype studio in New York, New York. The following year he established his gallery of illustrious Americans, which consisted of daguerreotype portraits of American celebrities, he published a portion as lithographic reproductions in 1850.
In 1849, Brady established a studio in Washington D.C., with the expectation of creating portraits of senators and congressional representatives, but he closed it within a year due to high operating expenses and local competition. While in Washington, he met Juliette Handy, whom he married two years later. Around this time, Brady's eyesight began to fail and he concentrated on the management of his studios, which included posing sitters for their portraits, while employees created the photographs. In 1853, he opened a second studio in New York, New York.
In 1858, Brady re-established a studio in Washington D.C., with Alexander Gardner as his primary photographer. With the onset of the American Civil War, Brady organized a corps of photographers and assistants to document the people, events, and locales of the war. Photographers in this group included George N. Barnard, Alexander Gardner, James Gardner, Timothy H. O'Sullivan, William Pywell, and Thomas C. Roche. The photographers created conventional portraits of individuals and groups, views of military encampments, and the aftermath of battles. Images published or adapted as engravings in publications had the credit "Photograph by Brady."
Brady sought to market images of the American Civil War with little success. During the war, he transferred many original glass plate negatives to the photographic supply firm of E. & H. T. Anthony & Company to settle his debts with the company. In 1942, the Library of Congress purchased much of this material, where it became the Anthony-Taylor-Rand-Ordway-Eaton Collection.
Brady spent an estimated $100,000 to print ten thousand photographic prints documenting the American Civil War, but a lack of customers required him to sell his studios in New York and Washington and declare bankruptcy. In 1875, he finally sold a bulk of his photographs to the United States government for $25,000. Much of this material became part of the files of the Department of War eventually deposited in the United States National Archives and Records Administration. Nevertheless, Brady remained deeply in debt.
By 1883, Brady formed a photographic partnership with his nephew, Levin Corbin Handy, and Samuel C. Chester, to market images from the American Civil War and maintain a photographic studio in Washington. In 1887, Juliette Handy Brady died. Brady continued to face financial difficulties through the remainder of his life. On January 15, 1896, Brady died in the charity ward of Presbyterian Hospital in New York, New York, from complications following a streetcar accident. After his death, his remaining photography files became the property of Levin Corbin Handy.
Levin Corbin Handy (1855-1932)
Levin Corbin Handy (1855-1932), an American photographer, was a nephew and former apprentice of Mathew B. Brady.
Born in Washington, D.C., the son of Samuel S. Handy and Mary A. Handy, Handy began working in the Brady studio as an apprentice in 1867. He soon demonstrated himself as a skilled camera operator, and established his own photographic business in Washington by 1871.
Around 1880, Handy entered a photographic partnership with Samuel C. Chester. They operated a studio in Cape May, New Jersey in 1882. By 1883, Handy and Chester partnered with Brady to market images from the American Civil War. Chester ultimately left the partnership, while Handy maintained the studio at his home and studio located at 494 Maryland Avenue Southwest, Washington, D.C. When Mathew B. Brady died in 1896, his remaining photography files became the property of Handy.
In Washington, the L.C. Handy Studio offered an array of traditional photographic services, in particular to the Library of Congress and other governmental agencies. He also provided photograph duplication services to patrons of the Library of Congress and to members of the United States Congress.
Handy died at his home on March 23, 1932. He bequeathed his studio and photographic files, including his collection of Mathew B. Brady, to his daughters, Alice H. Cox and Mary H. Evans. In 1954, the Library of Congress purchased approximately ten thousand original, duplicate, and copy negatives from Cox and Evans.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists primarily of photographs created by the studios of Mathew B. Brady and his nephew and former apprentice, Levin Corbin Handy, in Washington, D.C.
The collection includes imagery created by photographers employed by Brady during the American Civil War and documents his marketing of that imagery, as well as the continuing efforts of the Levin C. Handy Studio to promote and market this wartime imagery into the early twentieth century. The collection also documents the functioning of photographic studios in Washington, D.C., from the middle of the nineteenth century to the early twentieth century, and the personal photography and papers of the Handy family. The collection includes the work of other photographers and photographic studios collected by Handy, as well as artifacts related to photography.
This collection largely represents photographic material retained by Handy's daughters. Other photographic materials created by Brady and his studios were transferred to creditors during the American Civil War, purchased by the United States government in 1875, or purchased by Library of Congress in 1954. At the time of processing this collection, many of the images created by the Brady studio were available in digital form from the United States National Archives and Records Administration and the Library of Congress via the Internet.
Each folder in the collection contains a single photographic print, except where two or more photographic prints are noted, and each sleeve contains a single photographic negative, except where two or more film negatives are noted.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Mathew B. Brady Studio. II. Levin Corbin Handy Studio. III. Family Papers and Photographs. IV. Collected Photographs and Artifacts.
Within each series, the photographic materials are arranged according to format and presentation.
Photographers -- Washington (D.C.); Photographic industry; Portrait photographers -- Washington (D.C.); War photographers; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Pictorial works; Washington (D.C.) -- Pictorial works; Albums (Books); Copy prints; Gelatin dry plate negatives; Gelatin silver negatives; Photographic prints; Wet collodion negatives; Brady, Mathew B., approximately 1823-1896; Handy, Levin C. (Levin Corbin), 1855-1932; Jarvis, J. F. (John Fillis), 1849-1931; Russell, Andrew J., 1829-1902; L. C. Handy Studio; Underwood & Underwood
- Mathew B. Brady Studio, circa 1860-1885; Series I; (18 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of photographic prints from the studio of Mathew B. Brady in Washington, D.C. The photographs include studio and exterior portraits of officers serving in the military during the American Civil War; exterior views of battlefields, structures, and military units; and studio portraits of persons in the extended Brady and Handy families. The same image may exist in several subseries.
  Many images created by the studio of Mathew B. Brady exist in derivative forms in Series II. Levin Corbin Handy Studio.
  Arrangement
  Subseries are arranged by relative size of the photographic prints from small to large, with mounted prints preceding unmounted prints in each size. Photographic negatives, arranged by size, are listed following the prints.
  Subseries are arranged in the following manner:
  Cartes-de-visite
  Stereographs
  Albumen Photographic Prints, Mounted
  Photographic Prints Mounted on Square Plain Board
  Unmounted Photographic Prints of Officer Portraits
  Photographic Prints on Plain Board
  Photographic Prints on Blue Board Mounts
  Albumen Photographic Prints on "Original Photographs" Mounts
  Albumen Photographic Prints, Unmounted
  Oversize, Multiple Photographic Prints Mounted on Blue Board
  Oversize, Single Photographic Prints Mounted on Blue Board
  Oversize, Single Photographic Prints Mounted on Black Board
  Oversize, Photographic Prints Mounted on Plain Board
  Oversize, Albumen Prints, Unmounted
  Glass Photographic Negatives, Cartes-de-visite
  Glass Photographic Negatives, Carte-de-visite strip negatives, 3.5" X 7.5"
  - Cartes-de-visite, (31 photographic prints)
    Albumen photographic prints created by photographers employed by the studio of Mathew B. Brady mounted on carte-de-visite boards that primarily depict persons in the extended Brady and Handy families, circa 1860-1880.
    The series includes two cabinet photographs consisting of a portrait of Adlai Ewing Stevenson and an unidentified girl.
    Except where noted, the images are studio portraits. Most have manuscript inscriptions in pencil on their verso.
    Arranged alphabetically by the surname of the subject and then alphabetically by the subject matter.
    - Bright, John Fulmore, (2 photographic prints) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Darlington, Joseph J. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Fullmore, Ann (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Gessford, Harry L. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Handy, Emma Susannah (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Handy, George K. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Handy, Levin Corbin, (3 photographic prints) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Handy, Levin Corbin, probably, exterior portrait of him mounted on a horse, with Emma Sussanah Handy and an unidentified young woman (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Handy, Mary Ann (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Handy, Samuel Stratton (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Handy, William Brady (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Hayes, Rutherford Birchard (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Kendall, Amos (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Biographical/Historical note
      United States Postmaster General, 1835-1840
    - Knapp, Mollie, exterior portrait with Willie McDonald (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Little Maggie, Orange Girl of the Criminal Court (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Philips, Willie, exterior portrait with a horse (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Smith, John C. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Pastor of the Fourth Presbyterian Church, Washington, District of Columbia
    - Smith, Rebecca (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Stevenson, Adlai Ewing, (1 cabinet photograph) (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - United States Congress. Impeachment Committee of the House of Representatives, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      General note
      Left to right, standing, James Falconer Wilson, George Sewall Boutwell, and John Alexander Logan, seated, Benjamin Franklin Butler, Thaddeus Stevens, Mason Weare Tappan, and John Armor Bingham
    - Yates, Josie (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified persons
      - Girl, (1 cabinet photograph) (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Boy (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Woman (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Animals
      - Canaries on a ladder and balanced on a small log, (2 photographic prints) (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Dog (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - River (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Albumen Photographic Prints, Mounted, (11 photographic prints)
    Studio portraits mounted on cardboard that depict officers in the United States military, except where noted, during the American Civil War.
    Arranged alphabetically by the surname of the subject
    - Barlow, Francis Channing (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Butler, Benjamin Franklin (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Cox, Jacob Dolson (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Fry, Speed Smith (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Hill, Ambrose Powell (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Longstreet, James, Confederate States of America (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Powell, William Henry (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Ruffin, Edmund, Confederate States Army (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Stuart, James Ewell Brown, Confederate States Army (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Thomas, George Henry, posed sitting and his assistant posed standing (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Group portrait of generals (Box 2, Folder 38)
      Including left to right, standing back row, Alpheus Starkey Williams and Jefferson Columbus Davis, and sitting, Absalom Baird, James Sidney Robinson, Henry Alanson Barnum
  - Stereographs, (21 photographic prints)
    Albumen stereographic photographic prints created by photographers employed by the studio of Mathew B. Brady mounted on cardboard of images that primarily depict locations, persons, and events of the American Civil War, circa 1860-1865. Most have manuscript inscriptions in pencil on their verso.
    Arranged alphabetically by geographical location.
    - Georgia
      - Fort McAllister. Signal station on the Ogeechee River, 1864 Dec (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Kennesaw Mountain, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Maryland, Sharpsburg. Cavalry orderly, 1862 Oct (Box 3, Folder 41)
      Photograph by Alexander Gardner
    - Mississippi, Vicksburg. Levee and steamboats, 1864 Feb (Box 3, Folder 42)
      Photograph by William Redish Pywell
    - Pennsylvania, Gettysburg
      - Dead soldiers (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Union Army dead on the field of battle of first day (Box 3, Folder 44)
        Photograph by James F. Gibson
      - Union Army dead on the right of their line (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Trees (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Tennessee, Chattanooga. Buildings and railroad tracks, (3 photographic prints) (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Virginia, Aiken's Landing. Double-turreted monitor USS Onondaga on the James River (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Virginia, Alexandria. Battery Rodgers. 15-inch Redman gun (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Virginia, Bull Run
      - Men on bank of the river, by a log bridge, and cannonball (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Men on high banks of the river (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Men on rocks of the river (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Virginia, City Point
      - Railroad yard and transports (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - Supply wagons of 2nd Brigade, 2nd Corps (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Virginia, Petersburg
      - Headquarters, 50th New York Engineers, 1864 Nov (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - Heavy gun mounted on inner line of Confederate fortifications (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - Interior of colonial mansion on Bollingbrook street, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Photographic Prints Mounted on Square Plain Board, (18 photographic prints)
    Photographic prints created by photographers employed by the studio of Mathew B. Brady mounted on square-shaped cardboard of images that primarily depict locations, persons, and events of the American Civil War, circa 1860-1865. Many have pencil inscriptions describing the image on their verso.
    Arranged alphabetically by geographical location of the subject.
    - Pennsylvania, Gettysburg. Three Confederate prisoners (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Tennessee, Chattanooga. Missionary Ridge, 200-pound battery (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Tennessee, Tennessee River. Transports ascending rapids (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Virginia, Bull Run. Log buildings (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Virginia, Harrison's Landing. Exterior portrait of Samuel Peter Heintzelman and his staff (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Virginia, James River
      - USS Hunchback, two of the ship's officers seated in folding chairs on the upper deck (Box 4, Folder 63)
      - USS Lehigh, officers on deck (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - USS Mendota (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Virginia, Petersburg. Dead Confederate soldier outside the walls of Fort Mahone, 1865 Apr 3 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Virginia, Spotsylvania County, near Spotsylvania Court House. Dead Confederate soldiers collected for burial, 1864 May 19 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Virginia, Warrenton. Exterior portrait of Alfred Pleasonton, 1863 Oct (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Unidentified locations
      - Four naval officers posed sitting on the deck of a ship (Box 4, Folder 69)
      - Gun squad on a monitor, (3 photographic prints) (Box 4, Folder 70)
      - Ironworks on a monitor (Box 4, Folder 71)
      - USS Mahopac, naval officers on deck (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - USS Mendota, naval officers on deck (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - Unmounted Photographic Prints of Officer Portraits, (77 photographic prints)
    Unmounted studio portraits that depict officers in the United States military, except where noted. Many of the prints have pencil inscriptions on their versos identifying the individual in the image.
    Arranged alphabetically by the surname of the subject followed by unidentified subjects.
    - Arnold, Lewis Golding (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Bowen, Thomas Meade (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Bross, John A. (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Burnett, Henry Lawrence (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Burnham, Hiram (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Campbell, William Bowen (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Capehart, Henry (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Catterson, Robert Francis (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Champlin, Stephen Gardner (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Chapin, Edward Paayson (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Cook, John (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Cutcheon, Byron Mac (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Dawes, Rufus Robinson (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Delafield, Richard (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Dennis, Elias Smith (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Duval, Isaac Hardin (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Enochs, William Henry (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Force, Manning Ferguson (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Garrar, Theophilus Toulmin (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Gleason, Newell (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Harland, Edward (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Harris, Benjamin Foster (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Haskell, Lewellyn Frost (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Haynie, Isham Nicholas (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Heckman, Charles Adam (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Hough, John (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Howe, John Homer (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Jackson, William Lowther, Confederate States of America (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - McCook, Daniel (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - McCook, Robert Latimer (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Mindil, George Washington (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Newport, Reece Marshall (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Nicholls, S. W. (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Nickerson, Franklin Stebin (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Paine, Charles Jackson (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Paine, Eleazer Arthur (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Pease, Phineas (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Phelps, John Wolcott (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Pinto, Francis Effingham (Box 5, Folder 112)
    - Ratliff, Robert Wilson (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Raynor, William Henry (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Rice, Elliott Warren (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Rice, Samuel Allen (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Rodman, Isaac Peace (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Ruggles, Daniel, Confederate States of America (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Salomon, Frederick Sigel (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Sanders, William Price (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Scott, George Washington (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Shepard, Isaac Fitzgerald (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Sherman, Francis Trowbridge (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Sherwood, Isaac Ruth (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Slack, James Richard (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Smith, Andrew Jackson (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Spears, James Gallant (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - Stevens, Walter Husted, Confederate States of America (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Stevenson, John Dunlap (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Stokes, James Hughes (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Stuart, David (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Stumbaugh, Frederick Shearer (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Sullivan, Jeremiah Cutler (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - Trotter, Frederick Eugene (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Vail, Jacob Garetson (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Vandever, William, (2 photographic prints) (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Ward, George Hull (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Washburn, Francis (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Williams, David Henry (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Williams, Seth (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Wister, Langhorne (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Woodbury, Daniel Phineas (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Unidentified officer, Confederate States of America (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Unidentified officers, (6 photographic prints) (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - Photographic Prints on Plain Board, (27 photographic prints)
    Albumen photographic prints created by photographers employed by the studio of Mathew B. Brady mounted on cardboard that primarily depict locations, persons, and events of the American Civil War, circa 1860-1865. Most have manuscript inscriptions in pencil on their verso.
    Arranged alphabetically by geographical location of the subject followed by photographic prints with unidentified locations.
    - District of Columbia, Washington. Harewood Hospital (Box 6, Folder 145)
    - Georgia, Atlanta. Destroying a railroad (Box 6, Folder 146)
    - Mississippi River. Gunboat (Box 6, Folder 147)
    - Pennsylvania, Gettysburg. Exterior portraits
      - John S. Eckel, 50th Pennsylvania Infantry (Box 6, Folder 148)
      - Samuel K. Schwenk, 50th Pennsylvania Infantry mounted on a horse (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - Pennsylvania, Hanover Junction. Men and women at the train station (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - South Carolina, Charleston. Hibernian Hall (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - South Carolina, Morris Island. 200-pound gun used for shelling Charleston, South Carolina (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - Virginia, Alexandria
      - Blanket boats ferrying soldiers across the Potomac River (Box 6, Folder 153)
      - Sanitary Commission lodge (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - Virginia, Aquia Creek. Supply boats (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - Virginia, Bealeton. Henry Page, assistant quartermaster, (2 photographic prints) (Box 6, Folder 156)
    - Virginia, Brandy Station. Rufus Ingalls (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - Virginia, Centreville. Camp with soldiers, log buildings, horses and wagons, during winter of 1861-1862 (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - Virginia, Falls Church. Church (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - Virginia, James River.USS Lehigh, (2 photographic prints) (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Virginia, Petersburg
      - Fort Mahone (Box 6, Folder 161)
      - Exterior portrait of Frank Vane and horse, Independent Cavalry Regiment New York, Company Oneida (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - Virginia, Richmond. Fort Burnham/Fort Harrison (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Virginia, Stevensburg. Exterior portrait of Hugh Judson Kilpatrick and his staff (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - Unidentified locations